Guide to the Ron Loewinsohn Papers Papers, 1953-1976
Department of Special Collections
Loewinsohn, Ron. Papers,
1953-1976
M0856
Loewinsohn, Ron.
6 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The collection contains correspondence, published and unpublished manuscripts between American poet Ron Loewinsohn and many of the most prominent American authors of the mid-to-late 20th Century.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1996.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1996.
Biography
Ron Loewinsohn has been associated with San Francisco poetry since the late 1950s. In the early 1960s he taught at San Francisco State College, and in 1963 he co-edited and published the little magazine Change with Richard Brautigan. Loewinsohn's poems first achieved a wide readership by virtue of their inclusion in Donald Allen's anthology, The New American Poetry. His first book, Watermelons, contains an introduction by Allen Ginsberg and a letter from William Carlos Williams. Loewinsohn acknowledges both writers as his major influences, along with Robert Creeley and Philip Whalen. A later collection of poems, L'Autre, was the first full-length publication of the Black Sparrow Press. Loewinsohn's later publications include Meat Air and Goat Dances, both of which are collections of poetry. A complete checklist of Loewinsohn's primary publications is included in Gary Lepper's Bibliographical Introduction to 75 Modern American Authors. Ronald William Loewinsohn was born December 15, 1937, in Iloilo, Philippines and came to the United States with his parents in 1945. After he graduated from high school in 1955, he traveled around the country and then worked at various printing jobs, before instructing at the San Francisco Poetry Center, 1960-61. He attended San Francisco State College and earned his bachelor's degree from University of California, Berkeley in 1967. Loewinsohn then again instructed poetry at the Center for Adult Education in Cambridge, Mass., in the summer of 1968. He earned his master's and doctorate from Harvard University, in 1969 and 1971, respectively. Loewinsohn returned to Berkeley where he received a professorship in the English Department teaching American literature and creative writing, beginning in 1970. Ron Loewinsohn's awards and honors include the Poets Foundation Award (1963), the Irving Stone Award of the Academy of American Poets (1966), and the Ina Coolbrith Memorial Prize for Poetry (1966).
Scope and Content
The Ron Loewinsohn Papers primarily consist of correspondence collected by Loewinsohn over more than two decades, as well as materials concerning both published and unpublished manuscripts. The primary group of correspondence is from contemporary authors and artists, including Robert Creeley, Denise Levertov, Philip Whalen, and others. Some letters, including those from Allen Ginsberg and William Carlos Williams were not identified in the original listing. Additionally, there is a wealth of correspondence from personal acquaintances, students, and family not directly involved in the San Francisco and New York poetry scenes of the 1960s. Loewinsohn also received a considerable amount of correspondence from universities with which he was affiliated and publishers regarding his works. The materials pertaining to Loewinsohn's published manuscripts concern several major works. These include, L'Autre, Meat Air, Goat Dances, and Loewinsohn's doctoral thesis on the life and influence of William Carlos Williams titled The Province of a Poem (William Carlos Williams and the Invention of America). The unpublished manuscripts series includes many drafts of poems and short stories, and ideas for more of the same. Notebooks kept by Loewinsohn and his second wife, Joanie, have observations and ideas for works, as well as personal notes. Also, a large portion of poetry was found in a series of folders labeled "Hopper," "Master Hopper," "Asleep," "Dead," "Dead and Buried," and so on. These folder titles supply some insight into projects Loewinsohn may have been considering for the future, and other projects he had set aside.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Blackburn, Paul.; Brautigan, Richard.; Corso, Gregory.; Creeley, Robert, 1926-; Duerden, Richard.; Irby, Kenneth, 1936-; King, Basil.; Koch, Kenneth, 1925-; Kyger, Joanne.; Levertov, Denise, 1923-; Olson, Charles, 1910-1970.; Palmer, Michael.; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Stanley, George, 1934-; Wah, Fred, 1939-; Whalen, Philip.; Wieners, John, 1934-; American literature--20th century.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Personal Correspondence (1953-74)
  includes letters from noteworthy acquaintances
  - Blackburn, Paul (1965-70) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brautigan, Richard (1967-68) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Corso, Gregory (1958) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Creeley, Robert (1956-69) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Duerden, Richard (1963-68) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ginsberg, Allen (1971-72) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Irby, Ken (1963-64) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - King, Basil (1958-59) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - King, Basil (1960-65) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - King, Basil (1966-67) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - King, Basil (1968-70) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - King, Basil (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Koch, Kenneth (1965, 1969) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Kyger, Joanne - also Joanne Kyger Boyce (1965-69) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Levertov, Denise - also Denise Levertov Goodman (1964-70) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Olson, Charles (1963, 1968) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Palmer, Michael (1969-75) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Snyder, Gary (1966-74) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Stanley, George (1959-61) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Wah, Fred (1963-66) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Whalen, Philip (1958-68) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wieners, John (1957) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Williams, William Carlos (1953) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 2. General Correspondence from Individuals (1959-76)
  includes letters from acquaintances and friends including authors, students, friends, etc.
  - Allen, Donald (1968-71) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Allen, John (1969-70) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - André, Michael (1972-73) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Berrigan, Daniel and the Catsonville 9 (1968) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bromige, David (1967-74) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Byrd, Max (1970-73) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Carpenter, Don (1967-69) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Carr, Sue Loewinsohn (1967-69) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Coleman, Victor(1965-70) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Collom, Jack (1968-76) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Contoski, Victor (1970) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Corbett, Bill (n.d.) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Crozier, Andrew (1964, 1968) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Davidson, Michael (1968-75) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Enslin, Theodore (1976) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Flanagan, Thomas (1973-75) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Gartrell, Yvonne (1975) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Gelpi, Albert (1972-73) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Gerber, Dan (1971-72) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Goldfarb, Sydney (1971, 1975) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Goodman, Mitch (1967, 1971) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Gore, Patty (1970-74) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Graham, Theodora (1975-76) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hartman, Chuck (1970-72) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Harvey, Emily Wallace (1970-72) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Hass, Bob (1969-70) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Hoekzema, Loren (1969) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Hogg, Bob (1966-70) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - James, Tom (1971-74) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Jusawalla, Feroza (1974-75) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Keller, James(1971-72) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - L'Heureux (1970) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Longvilles, Tim (1972) (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Matlin, David (1972-73) (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Martin, John/Black Sparrow Press (11/66-5/67) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Martin, John/Black Sparrow Press (6/67-2/68) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Martin, John/Black Sparrow Press (3/68-12/68) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Martin, John/Black Sparrow Press (1969-71) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Martin, John/Black Sparrow Press (1972-74) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Martin, John/Black Sparrow Press (1975-76) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - McClung, Bill - UC Berkeley Press (1974-75) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Menasche, Samuel (1975-76) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Nichols, James (1970) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Parkinson, Thomas (1969-72) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Parrott, Jerry - Rain (1971) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Porte, Joel (1970-71) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Reed, Iva (1971-73) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Rosenthal, Les (1971) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Rowan, Luis (1966-69) (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Sage, Peter (1970-71) (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Scalopino, Leslie (1972-74) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Shideler, Ross (1967-68) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Skolnick, Paul (1974-75) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Sorrentino, Gilbert (1959-74) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Torrance, Bob (1969) (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Vas Dias, Robert (1969-74) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Wachtel, Andi (1972) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Webster, Tom - Spectrum (1970-71) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Williams, Florence - Mrs. William Carlos Williams (1963, 1970) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Winner, Ellen (1971) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Wittig, Susan (1968-69) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Zimmerman, Elaine (n.d.) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Zimmerman, Gerry (1963) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Zimmerman, Jo (1969-76) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - correspondence from Ron Loewinsohn w/ poems (1970, 1972) (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series 3. General Correspondence from Organizations
  includes universities, publishers, bookstores, etc.
  - Arizona State University (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Aspen Leaves (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Bureau Hungrois Pour la Protection des Droits D'Auteur (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Chicago Review (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - City Lights Bookstore (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Danforth Foundation (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Scott Foresman & Co. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Foruming Press (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Franconia (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Fybate Lecture Notes (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Harcourt Brace Jovanovich (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Harcourt, Brace and World (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Harvard University (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Haverford College (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - New Directions (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Ohio Review (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Phoenix Book Shop (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Poetry (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Resist (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - San Francisco Foundation Awards Office (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Sumac Press (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Tri-Quaterly (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Unicorn Press (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - University of California at Berkeley (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - University of California Committee on Prizes (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - University of California at Davis: Committee for Arts and Lectures (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Series 4. Miscellaneous Correspondence (1962-76)
  all correspondence which was not included in the prior series (solitary letters from unknown individuals, etc.)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1962-66 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1967-68 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1969-70 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1973-74 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence n.d. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - envelopes without letters (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Series 5. Dated and Published Manuscripts
  includes TS, MS, proofs, etc. of 9 major works
  - The World of the Lie (1963) - TS, dupes & notes (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - L'Autre (1967) - notes, poetry, & prose; TS & MS from folder labeled "L'Autre" (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - L'Autre (1967) - incomplete TS from folder labeled "Carbons & Dupes" (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - L'Autre (1967) - incomplete TS w/ corrections (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - The Step - TS w/ corrections (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - The Step - TS w/ corrections (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - The Step - carbon TS (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - The Province of a Poem (1957-69) - pp.i-41 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - The Province of a Poem (1957-69) - pp.42-83 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - The Province of a Poem (1957-69) - pp.84-124 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The Province of the Poem (different version) - intro to book on William Carlos Williams (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - William Carlos Williams and the Invention of America - "Tracking William Carlos Williams' Early Development," TS, 29pp. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - WCW... - TS & MS notes (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - WCW... - draft, chapter titled "Kora in Hell" (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 1, pp.1-43 - earliest draft (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 2, "Williams as Keats," pp.1-30 - earliest draft (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 3, "Williams as Pound," pp.1-33 - earliest draft (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 4, "Williams as Walt Whitman," pp.1-47 - earliest draft plus notes (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - WCW... - "Kora in Hell," MS & heavily corrected TS, limited organization (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - WCW... - from folder labled "Kora (RAW)," TS & MS, heavily corrected, in several different stages without organization (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - WCW... - random pages of TS w/ corrections (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - WCW... - notes, drafts of Preface, MS & TS w/ corrections (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 1, "WCW and the Invention of America," pp.1-40, TS w/ corrections, MS sources (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 2, "Williams as John Keats," pp.1-28, TS w/ corrections, MS sources (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 3, "Williams as Ezra Pound," pp.1-30, TS w/ corrections, MS sources (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 4, "Williams as Walt Whitman," pp.1-46, TS w/ corrections (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 5, "Williams and the Religion of Art," pp.1-20, TS w/ corrections (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - William Carlos Williams and the Invention of America - Chapt. 6, "Williams as Kora," pp.1-64, TS w/ corrections (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 7, "Williams as Nobody," pp.1-34, TS w/ corrections (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 8, "Williams as WCW," pp.1-58, TS w/ corrections (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 9, "The Province of the Poem," pp.1-23, and Bibliography, pp.241-246, both TS w/ corrections (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - WCW... - Preface, pp.i-vi, TS w/ corrections (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 1, "WCW and the Invention of America," pp.1-43, TS w/o corrections (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 2, "Williams as John Keats," pp.1-30, TS w/o corrections (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 3, "Williams as Ezra Pound," pp.1-33, TS w/o corrections (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 4, "Williams as Walt Whitman," pp.139, TS w/o corrections (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - WCW... - beginning of Chapt. 5, "Williams as Kora," pp.1-7, TS w/o corrections (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - WCW... - notebooks with MS drafts of chapters (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - WCW... - draft of chapter titled "Sour Grapes," pp.1-34, TS heavily corrected (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 1, "WCW and the Invention of America," pp.1-42, TS w/ corrections (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 2, "Poems, 1909," pp.1-27, TS heavily corrected (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 3, "The Tempers," pp.1-30, TS heavily corrected (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 4, "Al Que Quiere," pp.1-42, TS heavily corrected (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 1, "WCW and the Invention of America," pp.1-42, TS lightly corrected (best version) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 2, "Poems, 1909," pp.43-63, TS lightly corrected (best) (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 3, "The Tempers," pp.64-92, TS lightly corrected (best) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 4, "Al Que Quiere," pp.93-137, TS lightly corrected (best) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 5, "Sour Grapes," pp.138-171, TS lightly corrected (best) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - WCW... - Chapt. 6, "Spring and All," pp.172-222, TS lightly corrected (best) (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Melville and the Greeks (1967) - TS w/ corrections, 49pp. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Record Book (1968-74) - MS, drafts of poems, w/ insertions (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Meat Air (1970) - TS heavily corrected, pp.i-41 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Meat Air - TS heavily corrected, pp.42-83 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Meat Air - TS heavily corrected, pp.84-124 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Meat Air (1970) - proofs, marked set (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Meat Air - galleys, w/ corrections (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Meat Air - proofs (later version) w/o corrections (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Meat Air - bound edition, labeled "Advance Uncorrected Proofs" (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Goat Dances (1976) - bound, photocopied TS, 116pp. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Series 6. Unpublished Manuscripts
  includes TS, MS, notes, short stories, and poetry
  - Personal Statement (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - The Truck - scenario, corrected TS, about 100pp. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Notebook (1966-68) (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Notebook (n.d.) - possibly including both Ron and Joanie Loewinsohn's handwriting (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - The World Series - TS story w/ few corrections, 25pp. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Dementia (1956-57) - TS & MS, poetry and prose (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - The Snow - TS short story found in folder labeled "The Cooker" (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Poetry - TS & MS w/ corrections found in folder labeled "Master Hopper" (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Poetry - TS & MS w/ corrections found in folder labeled "Hopper" (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Poetry - TS & MS w/ corrections found in folder labeled "Asleep" (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Poetry and prose - TS found in folder labeled "Dead" (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - After the (Mimeograph) Revolution - TS story found in folder labeled "Dead" (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Poetry "to Raymond DiPalma" found in folder labeled "Dead" (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Poetry and prose - TS & MS found in folder labeled "Dead and Buried" (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Poetry, prose, notes, etc. - TS & MS from folder labeled "Notes & Stuff" (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Poetry, prose, etc. - TS found in folder labeled "Carbons - Dupes" (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - 2 Poems with note "to Ellie" & 1 poem, alone (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Poetry, prose, notes, etc. - TS & MS w/o any organization (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Poetry, prose, notes, etc. - TS & MS w/o any organization (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Limekiln Creek - TS draft with lots MS notes/corrections on reverse (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Limekiln Creek - pp.1-37, TS w/ corrections (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Limekiln Creek - pp.38-74, TS w/ corrections (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Limekiln Creek - pp.75-111, TS w/ corrections (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Limekiln Creek - pp.112-148, TS w/ corrections (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Limekiln Creek - pp.149-185, TS w/ corrections (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - The Leaves [10] - poetry, TS w/ corrections, 3pp. (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - In the Library - story, TS w/ corrections, 9pp. (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Number 10 - story, 2 very different drafts, both TS (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Food for Thought - script, 2 copies, both TS, one with comments (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - "The Glamour of the Real, The Commodious Adjective" - paper written and submitted by Ramon Fernandez for the Helen Choate Bell Prize - probably reviewed by Loewinsohn as member of Prize Committee (Box 12, Folder 20)